그럴려면 비밀을 밝히기 전에 비밀을 말할 거라고 말했어야죠
Well,I'm sorry,but you would have had to express that desire before revealing the secret,
그래야 비밀 보호 계약을 이행할 지 내가 결정할 수 있잖아요
so that I could choose whether or not I wanted to accept the covenant of secret keeping.
일단 말하고 강요하면 안 되요
You can't impose a secret on an ex post facto basis.
뭐라고요?
What?
비밀을 지키는 건 아주 힘든 노력이 필요해요
Secret keeping is a complicated endeavor.
무슨 말을 하는 지만 생각하는 것이 아니라
One has to be concerned not only about what one says,
얼굴 표정이라던가 자율 신경계의 반사 작용도 고려해야죠
but about facial expressions, autonomic reflexes.
거짓말을 해야할 때는 라임병 연구실에서보다 더 많이 경련이 일어나거든요
When I try to deceive,I myself have more nervous tics than a Lyme disease research facility.